Andrew Sweeney has written a lot about
Jordan Peterson and I've made quite a
few films about him since we started
following Jordan Peterson he's been
getting some quite intense criticism why
I caught up with Andrew to talk it
through I guess we've been engaging
pretty deeply with his thought for quite
a while and also reading a lot of the
criticisms and come to a view about why
it is that he provokes such a strong
reaction among so many people and what
that maybe says about his thoughts where
and what it says about the culture at
large what is it that he's saying that
seems to be so indigestible for some
people and is it and the parrot the
great paradox as well as that he a lot
of his thought talks about the necessity
of talking with people who don't agree
with the understanding that people have
different views based on the
temperaments and it seems to point a way
to to getting past some of the divisions
in the culture but the irony is he
himself has seemed to be an incredibly
divisive figure how do you make sense of
that kind of paradox okay well I think
the moment like the big moment right
where all this began is the big gotcha
moment and I don't mean with Kathy
Newman I mean with Trump I think Trump
was the gotcha moment for the culture
right it was the moment when the
progressive bubble burst
it was the moment when the progressive
got God and I so to speak right so I
think it's I've been thinking about this
in terms of you know how I was before
Trump was elected and you could say I'm
a I'm a sort of a political typical
progressive you know with the lesbian
mom and very much
you know pro-environment the post-modern
worldview there's something you know
empty about it right but it's also I
mean I've sort of framed it before as
the hidden shadow of liberalism it's
this kind of ideology of inclusivity
that also is a tribalism that won't
admit that it's a tribalism
we are very very tolerant to to
everybody except for traditionalists
right because there's this terrible fear
of traditionalism you know and
conservatism there's this intense fear
of progressives about religion
do you consider Peterson to be I mean
he's certainly arguing for
traditionalist values but but I think
there's something deeper like he's not
and he's often seen by a lot of people
that's the criticism he's a regressive
he's he's knocking back so I I think
actually what he's arguing for is a
slightly deeper integration of
traditional values my fence is with with
Peterson is that he doesn't really fit
into that culture war narrative so much
he's he's looking to transcend it in
some ways well exactly he's he's not a
pure traditionalist right he's not a
conservative you know in the purest
sense of that world he's not arguing
about going back to traditionalism he's
arguing about transcending and including
it to use Wilbur's language right he
wants to rescue the father right at the
bottom of the you know the whale this is
always the mythological terms he is he
wants to rescue this tradition no but he
that he doesn't he doesn't he's not
fully enclosed within it he's also a
very open progressive you know person
you know and he's also you know so I
think the reason he's so much in the
center of the discussion right now is
that he can see all the way all the way
down to the bottom right to the to the
base of the culture and he can also see
up right there's this verticality right
of his thinking so he understood he
understands that he understands the
progressive view and he understands a
postmodern view and he criticizes it's
pathology right I very you know strongly
that the postmodern view has become it's
reached it's sort of maximum you know
pathology it's become sick right he's
not just theorizing about the world he's
he's he's bringing an actual change to
people's lives that that is that it is
profound
it just whether you agree with him or
not like me I'm sure you've been accused
of being a JP fanboy and I I've been
really trying to engage with the
criticisms that I found and to really
interrogate my own view around him and
try and understand where the criticisms
are coming from and trying to sort of
say well are there spaces that he's not
seeing are there things that that he's
wrong about because Oh on the overview
if you look at something like maps of
meaning and the Bible lectures and you
really understand the the broader
outlines of his thought there's
something almost anti anti intellectual
about it because almost everything he's
saying is pointing back into the world
in some way it's saying look you're
already doing this look at the way your
your systems your meaning systems work
in the world look at the way you respond
to this piece of art look at this way
you respond to music and he's actually
put putting pieces together so there's a
kind of I find there's almost very
little there's very little pure
intellectual abstraction to argue with a
lot of the time it seems to be pointing
back into the world which i think is
quite infuriating for the people arguing
with him is that what he's saying seems
a lot of what he's saying is is kind of
unarguable and what I found in almost
all of the the pieces of criticism of
him or not without exception but but
generally without exception is there's a
real resentment in there and it comes
out very very quickly when you're
reading it it's either a sort of
dismissiveness or saying oh he's got
nothing worthwhile to say or or whatever
and you and it's really what's also
fascinating is that's a central part of
his thought and a central part of his
thought is to say pay attention to your
resentment it's telling you something
and the paradox is I'd say 95 percent if
not more of the criticisms that I've
read of him are permeated by this kind
of resentment
and it's it's really hard to get for me
it's really hard to get beyond that to
see whether they're saying anything
worthwhile when when there's a clearly
current some kind of a gender at play
yeah
the resentment I think comes from being
a hyper intellectual right if you live
in this theoretical world all the time
you know if your world you know a couple
of interviews are attacks on him i I've
read we're very very sophisticated and
there were there were a lot of good
points there right what these people are
extremely envious about and I would say
Envy you know rent as you read says Envy
is the one part of ourselves that we
can't we can't really look at we're too
if we're too afraid to admit that we're
envious and jealous of somebody and that
that that is our one of the biggest
blind spots of human beings is envy and
I believe this a lot of this the these
hyper intellectual people who are living
in very theoretical abstract you know
universes and but at the same time they
they've lost the ability to communicate
with the order of the common man you
know they've lost ability the ability to
bring their wisdom you could say down
from the mountain you know they're still
up there in the absolute the world of
abstraction right and they have an
embodied their their wisdom so Peterson
is a very embody type of type of thinker
yeah this is really interesting that you
make that connection to embodiment
because this is where I think I
resonated the most with Peterson because
I've done a lot of sort of deep
psychological work a lot of Jungian
shadow work about integration of the
shadow and that was really the subject
of my first interview with him was I'd
never heard anyone describe the process
of personal integration as clearly as
him and then to link that to this deep
story of the of the logos more aligned
with this sort of deep principle of
Western culture this was really exciting
for me and and suddenly started to make
sense
I mean I'd always done a lot of the work
that I'd done in a
slightly more I guess a more new-age
kind of way of talking about
spirituality and using young in in that
way and then to hear that kind of really
deeply connected to like the Christian
story and the the it really felt I was
grounding a lot of everything I knew
everything I knew most certainly that
I'd experienced myself and integrated
myself and an embodied in my own life
then suddenly had this intellectual
construct that just as Peterson says
about his lectures it just went click
click click click click and I felt this
sort of deeper intellectual integration
with something I had already embodied
and that's a that's a sense that I get I
mean very few people I think are
actually living a fully embodied and
fully living out their philosophy in the
world because it's such a difficult
thing to do it's such a difficult like
you say to look at your envi to look at
your resentment to really admit that
that you have it is a really difficult
process yeah well I think that the
shadow' notion is is absolutely
essential right it's it's an essential
notion right that needs to be
reintroduced to the to the culture we
need to stop looking for the shadow
outside of ourselves you know we need to
stop you know we need to stop with our
categories of people being this or that
and being bad and you know and our
self-righteousness and our you know all
of all of this and we need to admit in
our cells that were also the worst
person right he's bringing back
traditional ism and mysticism into the
conversation which is terrifying as hell
for people yeah who have do believe that
we've gone beyond that who we we've gone
to a new level of society we we've gone
beyond all these ignorant religions and
all these ignorant traditions and now we
are we're becoming more and more
enlightened and progressive and they
don't want to go back there and they
don't want to look you know back into
our origins but you know Peterson you
know he says it's not capitalism it's
it's deep in our origins where where
where the shadow lives where you know so
there's this unintegrated tradition in
the culture right this this is a really
profound point that that you mentioned
before and I thought was really worth
exploring about mysticism because there
is something like even in the the Pankaj
Mishra article where he talked about
fascist mysticism this there is this
huge fear among the sort of secular
materialist classes of what this means
to bring Europe from the depths for
example to talk about the archetypal
ground of religion to talk about the
mythological structures because there is
this sense that well we've we've we've
got rid of that and that has a checkered
history because there was something of
the occult behind say the fascists for
example there is some there is this sort
of a cult tradition that feeds off its
archetypal force of mythology and we've
banished that but there's also a sense I
think among a lot of people that in
banishing that we've also banished
spirituality we've also banished
religion we've also banished some deep
part of the human soul and maybe a lot
of what we're seeing playing out in the
culture right now the kind of is the end
of the age of materialism we sort of get
a sense of this multi-level crisis which
comes from seeing the world as only a
sort of set of material forces with no
deeper soul or spirit and it's it told
me you cannot sorry about that you
continue you can't even see the word
soul right it's it's taboo you can't
even say the word sacred it's taboo you
can't even talk about religion right you
can't even have a discussion about it
without offending a lot of people right
yeah and this is this is something I
think that uh a lot of people that I'm a
lot of the networks that I'm part of
talk about reanimating the world either
Deep Ecology or some of these sort of
forces of bringing a sense of the sacred
back into public life or into into
Western culture and then
they can't but they can't get past their
political response to Peterson to see
that's exactly what he's doing and he is
perhaps their best ally and the best
exponent of this kind of reanimating of
the sacred that you will ever that you
will ever have and his success shows the
thirst for the knit for that reanimation
of the sacred can you talk about that
kind of mysticism that he's bringing in
fear that it brings up I've been
practicing meditation for a while so so
I I do actual spiritual practice why did
they keep calling Peterson a fascist you
know and why is because fascism I guess
is a kind of you know dark mysticism
mm-hmm and and perhaps they're
legitimate to be to be afraid of this
but again they're focusing on the
pathology and they're not seeing the
enlightened aspects of mysticism I
mentioned this as a kind of a joke that
he's transgender you know it's a joke
and it's a provocation right because
I've noticed that he you know the things
he talks about her you know he talks
about cleaning your room you know who
cleans your room you know who tells you
to clean your room your mother right you
know he's he's very motherly he's very
maternal with people he cries about
young men you know he wants the best for
you know he's very caring right he's
very maternal but he's also very fierce
and masculine so he's he's sort of
integrated this masculine and feminine
rather than being just a hyper masculine
you know a chauvinistic man which a lot
of people are accusing him of being he's
integrated the male and the female which
makes them very powerful and put some
kind of in the center of both so he
could he can talk to that he can he can
he can communicate to both who men and
both women to the left and the right you
know he can have conversations with you
know conservatives like Shapiro and he
can also have conversations with you
know left-wing people like Russell Brand
Reich he can and and if he can so he
sort of he's transgender in the sense
that spiritually transgender in the
sense that he's integrated the male and
female inside of them and you know I I
think I don't know if people have
noticed this because he
always being accused of being you know
the patriarchy you know but I think he's
like yeah I think he's much more
postmodern than then then then he
pretends to be or that he really is
because he doesn't for example he
doesn't go to church but he's trying to
integrate the aspects of the Bible he
doesn't again I said that's in the
beginning I don't think he's a pure
traditionalist what's really interesting
for me from a very sort of broader
cultural perspective is where it seems
that we are in our attitude to religion
because we had for a long time the the
new atheist the Richard Dawkins and sam
Harris were certainly dominant online
and certainly very influential in kind
of as the gatekeepers of the culture
like in the kind of media world that
I've been part of talking about religion
talking about spirituality would always
get you wouldn't get something
commissioned because it's cynicism is a
very easy position to defend oh no one
sort of making those Commissioning
decisions at any kind of channel would
would want to open the door to religious
or spiritual content whereas out it it
really seems that with this kind of
evolving conversation that Jordan
Peterson is right at the center of there
is a certain understanding of the
function of religion even if you wanted
to reframe it within a sort of more
secular way of these are the best
stories of how to live our lives that
we've come up with and they're pointing
to something that we can achieve in our
own lives and there is there is
seemingly a shift in that conversation
around validity of religion and
spiritual experience that seems to work
very exciting to me yeah yeah because
yeah result he's opening the black tide
of mysticism right which this is what
this is what Freud accused Jung of doing
doing opening the black tide of
mysticism right there's this terror of
this right but there's also this
incredible potential again it may be you
could put it in this red religion you
know category which was very I think I
thought the blue church red religion
categories of
Jordan Curtin green Wallace's name are
perfect really the red with the red red
religion is is alive you know it's on
fire and is dangerous but the blue
religion is is suffocating and it's it's
full of orthodoxies which you know and
it's it becomes it's it's dead right
it's a dead world whereas whereas you
know Peterson's opening this flood of
possibility in terms of you know well
you know in terms of how we approach
approach missus ism but also from a
scientific point of view which is
interesting for me because I wouldn't
have naturally gone there myself